Guide to the Dept. of Human Development records,1937-2008.
Dept. of Human Development records, 1937-2008
- Series VI. Course Material
  - HDFS-NIMH-Site Visit- Graduate Students, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - HDFS-NIMH-Site Visit- Graduate Field Faculty and Graduate Courses, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - HDFS-NIMH-Site Visit- Graduate Seminars and Courses, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - HDFS-NIMH-Site Visit- Research, Student and Faculty Proposals, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - HDFS-NIMH-Site Visit- Info sent to prospective students; field handbook and minority information, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - HDFS-Master Plan, 1977-1980/1981-1985 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - HDFS-Doctoral Program in Developmental Psychology- State Review- Program, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - HDFS-Doctoral Program in Developmental Psychology- State Review- Faculty, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - HDFS-Doctoral Program in Developmental Psychology- State Review- Students, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - HDFS-Doctoral Program in Developmental Psychology- State Review, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - HDFS-Department of Ed. Psych Review, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Syllabi - HDFS 111: Observation, 1976-1990 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Syllabi - HDFS 116: Adolescence, 1975-1984 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - HDFS 117: Adult Developing and Aging, 1981-1984
    - HDFS 141: Introduction to Expressive Materials, 1981
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - HDFS 155: History of Childhood, 1988
    - HDFS 201: Analysis of Contemporary Issues, 1983
    - HDFS 212: Early Adolescence, 1980-1982
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Sociology 243: The Family, 1979
    - HDFS 270: Abnormal Development, 1979-1988
    - HDFS 302: Family and Community Health, 1970s
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - HDFS 307: Collective Behavior and Social Movements, 1979-1980
    - HDFS 315: Human Sexuality, 1980-1982
    - HDFS 331: Learning in Children, 1995
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - HDFS 338: Development of Creative Thinking, 1979-1981
    - HDFS 342: Models and Settings in Programs for Young Children, 1978-1982
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - HDFS 455: Minority Families, 1987
    - HDFS 352: Contemporary Family Forms, 1972-1980
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - HDFS 353: Family as a Context for Adult Development, 1976
    - HDFS 354: Family in a Cross Cultural Perspective, 1975-1996
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - HDFS 358: Theories of Adult Interpersonal Relationships, 1976-1983
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - HDFS 364: Psychology of Television, 1985-1990
    - HDFS 365: The Study of Lives, 1976-1981
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - HDFS 371: Behavioral Disorders of Childhood, 1982-1983
    - HDFS 380: Aging and Health, 1979-1982
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - HDFS 385: Women and the Family in Israel and the Arab World
    - HDFS 410: Fieldwork in Adolescent Development, 1978-1983
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - HDFS 414: Policies and Programs for Adolescents, 1980s
    - HDFS 418: Work and Human Development
    - HDFS 485: Human Development in Post-Industrial Societies, 1985-1986
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - HDFS 441: The Development of the Black Child, 1979-1981
    - HDFS 451: Innovative Programs of Parent Intervention and Community Action, 1979
    - HDFS 470: Field Experiments in Atypical Development, 1977
    - HDFS 481: Introduction to Ecological Psychology, 1985-1989
    - HDFS 483: Development in Context, 1983
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - HDFS 488: Human Development in Context, 1983-1988
    - HDFS 490: Historic Roots of Modern Psychology, 1977-1981
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - HDFS 600: Family Psychopathology, 1973-1976
    - HDFS 601: Research Methodology, 1977-1981
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - HDFS 602: Research Design and Data Analysis, 1976-1977
    - HDFS 603: Development in Context, 1975-1978
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - HDFS: The Course of Life, 1979-1984
    - HDFS 641: Early Childhood Education, 1976-1979
  - Syllabi (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - HDFS 665: Seminar in Personality and Social Development, 1980
    - HDFS 690: Seminar on the Ecology of Human Development, 1977
    - HDFS 701: Research Practicum - Women's Roles, 1980-1987
  - "Participation with Groups of Children in the Early Years"- HDFS 242- Sue West- Instructor, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Advanced Participation in Preschool Setting"- HDFS 348- Judy Ross-Bernstein- Instructor, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Learning in Children"- HDFS 431- Dr. Potts- Instructor, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "Thinking and Reasoning"- HDFS 438- Dr. Koslowski-Instructor, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "Nursery School Internship- HDFS 440- Sue West: "Families, Social Support, Aging and Health" -HDFS 455- Prof. Wethington- Instructor, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "Curiosity and Intrinsic Motivation" -HDFS 465 and Instruction and Research Practicum on Television- J. Condry- Instructor, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - "Critical Reading and Thinking" -HE 100- Dr. Selco-Instructor and "Determinants of Human Behavior" -HSS 246- Jeanne Mueller- Instructor, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "Infancy and Childhood" -HDFS 115-Phil Schoggen- Instructor and "Groups and Organizations" -HSS 203- TA instructor, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - HDFS 610: Processes in Human Development, 1991-11 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Lists: Graduates of PhD program, student publications, student college grants, predoctoral students, research grants, 1975-1984 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Field Study Abroad: Child Care and Family Policy in Sweden, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Series VII. Dept. Reviews
  - Department Review, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Department Review-Booklet, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - External Review, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Review- Introduction and Background, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Review- Undergraduate and Graduate Programs, Research, Outreach, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence concerning review and Human Development, 1996 (Box 10)
- Series VIII. Photographs, Slides
  - Faculty who attended SRCD Summer Institute - Another copy of this photo with people labeled can be found in box 3 of collection #23-13-2551, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Faculty at reception after completion of Henry Ricciuti's 2nd term as Chair, 1986 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Society for Research on Child Development (SRCD) Photographs, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Negatives, and File Prints of various faculty in the Department and at Department events, 1940s, and 1950s and some more recent (Box 12)
  - Slides and Script-"But What Do you Do With Them?" produced by Anne Willis and Joan Johnston and "Striving for Independence", 1972 (Box 28)
- Series IX. Intelligence Tests
  - Rorschach - Psychodiagnostik, 1937 (Box 15)
  - Book: The First Five Years of Life - Arnold Gesell, 1940 (Box 15)
  - Minnesota Preschool Scale, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Book: Examining for Aphasia - Jon Eisenson, 1946 (Box 30)
  - Book: Vineland Social Maturity Scale - Edgar Doll, 1947 (Box 30)
    Educational Test Bureau
  - Wechsler - WISC, 1948 (Box 15)
  - Columbia Mental Maturity Scale, 1954 (Box 18)
  - Book: Developmental Diagnosis - Arnold Gesell and Catherine Amatruda, 1956 (Box 15)
  - Holtzman Inkblot Technique, 1958 (Box 15)
  - Stanford-Binet Intelligence Scale, 1960 (Box 16)
  - Dvorine Pseudoisochromatic Plates, 1963 (Box 30)
  - Goldstein-Scheerer Tests, 1960-1965 (Box 15)
    object sorting set and stick tests
  - Gesell Developmental Schedules, 1964 (Box 17)
  - Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence Manual, 1967 (Box 30)
  - Illinois Test of Psycholinguistic Abilities, 1969 (Box 16)
  - Bayley Scales of Infant Development, 1969 (Box 31)
    The Psychological Corporation
  - McCarthy Scales of Children's Abilities, 1972 (Box 32)
  - Psychoeducational Evaluation of the Preschool Child Utilizing the Haeussermann Approach, 1972 (Box 30)
    Grune and Stratton
  - Book: A Clinical and Educational Manual for Use with the Uzgiris and Hunt Scales of Infant Psychological Development - Carl Dunst, 1980 (Box 30)
    University Park Press
  - Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test, 1981 (Box 30)
    Lloyd and Leota Dunn
  - Kaufman Assessment Battery for Children, 1983 (Box 33)
    American Guidance Service
- Series X. Colloquia and Symposiums
  - HDFS-Colloquium (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
  - Iscol lecture: "A Commitment to Social Change" Presenters: Rafael Cestero, Jonah Edelman and Katherine LaGuardia, 2001 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Iscol lecture: "Education for Social Justice the El Puente" Presenters: Luis Acosta and Frances Lucerna, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Iscol lecture: "A Harder Thing: Discovering My Work in East Harlem" Presenter: Ivan Hageman, 2003 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Iscol lecture: " A Light of Conscience: How a Simple Act Can Change Your Life" Presenter: Bill Shore, 2004 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Iscol lecture: "A Lifetime of Community Service- How Young People Are Becoming Active Citizens and Social Entrepreneurs" Presenter: Ken Grouf, 2005 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Ricciuti Symposium, 1989-10 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Ricciuti Symposium, 1989-10-06 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Future Direction in Infancy Research", Book from the Ricciuti Symposium, 1989-10-06 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Developmental Psychopathology Symposium, 1993-03 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Bretenthal Colloquium and Mineka Colloquium, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Schacter Colloquium (October 1998); Richard McCarty Colloquium (April 2000); Posner Colloquium (November 2000); Jerry Kagan Colloquium (April 2000) (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Mentoring Youth at Work Symposium, 2001 (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - Claire Wiseman Brown Bag (December 2000); Feerick and Snow Talk (November 2002); Kalil Seminar (April 2003); Lisa Diamond Talk (March 2004); Ruth Chao Talk (October 2005); Suomi Talk (April 1999); Martin Conway (February 2005) (Box 20, Folder 10)
- Series XI. Videos, Cassette Tape Recordings, DVDs
  - Extension Non-Broadcast Resources: Program 39: Workshop: Home Economics Program Committee: The Randell Family, V-6259
  - Video: Iscol Family Program for Leadership Development in Public Service: "Education for Social Justice: El Puente" - Luis Garden Acosta and Frances Lucerna, 2002-09-25; V-792
  - Video: Iscol Family Program for Leadership Development in Public Service: "A Harder Thing: Discovering My Work in East Harlem" - Ivan Hageman, 2003; V-827
  - Steve Ceci on ABCs 20/20, 1993-10; V-434
  - Steve Ceci on McNeil Lehrer News Hour, V-588
  - Cynthia Hazen Spot, V-589
  - Cynthia Hazen "Relationships in the 1990s", tr7808a
  - Eileen Trzcinski and Elaine Wethington - "Work and Family: Exploring the Issues", tr7807a
  - ISCOL Family Program for Leadership Development in Public Service, 2001-09-25; DVC-4
- Series XII. Extension Material
  - Extension Role/Voting in Human Development, 1979-2004 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Human Development and Family Studies Extension Report, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Expectations of Faculty with Extension Responsibilities (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Human Development and Family Studies Extension Programs, 1985 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Human Development Extensions- Human Ecology Examples, 1981-1997 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Cooperative Extension Service's Mission... Need Congressional Clarification, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Human Development and Family Studies External Review, 1985 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Land Grant Presentation to Human Development Faculty (Engman*) *additional Engman correspondence can be found in Cornell Migrant Campus Collection #23/13/3582 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Pathways from Poverty, 1995-1996 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Human Development Department Review (Extension Component), 1996 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Petition Signing in Cooperative Extension, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Animal Welfare and Animal Rights, 1986 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Human Development Extension "Position Paper" (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Future of the Cornell Cooperative Extension System, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Civil Rights at the U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Statewide Youth Programming Coordinating Council, 1998-1999 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Youth Development Statewide Program Committee, 1999-2000 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - 4-H Teen Programs- County Survey, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Parenting Second Time Around, 2000-2001 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Parenting the Second Time Around- Manual, 2001 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Parents Apart, 2000-2001 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Successful Stepfamilies, 2000-2001 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - Parenting Position in Human Development, 2000-2001 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - Meeting the Needs of the 21st Century (Committee), 1988 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - Human Ecology Voting Status, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - Youth Development/4-H in the 21st Century, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - Human Development Extension, 1989-1995 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - Human Development Space/Resource Applications, 1992-2003 (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - Human Development Chair's Advisory Committee, 1998-2000 (Box 21, Folder 29)
  - Human Development Extension Review, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 30)
  - Human Development Extension Review, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 31)
  - Agricultural Initiative/Vision for Engagement, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 32)
  - Human Development Extension Reports and Priorities, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 33)
  - Human Development Extension Reports and Plans, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 34)
  - Human Development Extension Reports and Priorities, 1999 (Box 21, Folder 35)
  - Human Development Extension Strategic Plan, 2000-2001 (Box 21, Folder 36)
  - Training for Front-Line Workers (Human Development), 2002 (Box 21, Folder 37)
  - Human Development Department Extension Retreats, 1984-1997 (Box 21, Folder 38)
  - Human Development Department Extension Faculty Retreat, 1998-1999 (Box 21, Folder 39)
  - Human Development Department Extension Retreat, 2000, 2001 (Box 21, Folder 40)
  - Human Development Department Extension Retreat, 2002 (Box 21, Folder 41)
  - Human Development Department Extension Retreat, 2003 (Box 21, Folder 42)
  - Human Development Extension Faculty Meetings, 2002-2006 (Box 21, Folder 43)
  - Status of Non-Tenure Track Faculty at Cornell, 2003 (Box 21, Folder 44)
  - College of Human Ecology Department Extension Leaders Meetings, 1983-1998 (Box 21, Folder 45)
  - Agent Faculty Committee- Department of Human Development, 1975-1979 (Box 21, Folder 46)
  - Agent Faculty Committee- Department of Human Development, 1980-1985 (Box 21, Folder 47)
  - Agent Faculty Committee- Department of Human Development, 1986-1989 (Box 21, Folder 48)
  - Herb Engman* Appointment as Department Extension Leader *additional Engman correspondence can be found in Cornell Migrant Campus Collection #23/13/3582, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 49)
  - Herb Engman* Presentations *additional Engman correspondence can be found in Cornell Migrant Campus Collection #23/13/3582, 1983, 1985 (Box 21, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence- Herb Engman* *additional Engman correspondence can be found in Cornell Migrant Campus Collection #23/13/3582, 1982-1984 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence- Herb Engman* *additional Engman correspondence can be found in Cornell Migrant Campus Collection #23/13/3582, 1980 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence- Herb Engman* *additional Engman correspondence can be found in Cornell Migrant Campus Collection #23/13/3582, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence- Herb Engman* *additional Engman correspondence can be found in Cornell Migrant Campus Collection #23/13/3582, 1985-1988 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence- Herb Engman* *additional Engman correspondence can be found in Cornell Migrant Campus Collection #23/13/3582, 1989-2006 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence- Florence Cherry, 1979-1980 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence- Florence Cherry, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Jennie Birckmayer (Post-Retirement), 1996-2001 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Human Development/Extension Resources for Educators, 2000 (Box 29, Folder 12-13)
- Series XIII. Programs
  - Family Development Training and Credentialing Program, 1996-1999 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Family Development Training and Credentialing Program, 2001 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Family Development Training and Credentialing Program, 2003; 2007 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Graduate Program - Description of Program, 1999-2006 (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Family Resolutions Project Practice Manual - Helping Families Plan For Their Children's Safety and Well-Being, 1998 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Family Resolutions Project Final Evaluation Report, 1998 (Box 29, Folder 11)
- Series XIV. Publications
  - Cornell Research Program in Early Development and Education-Publications and Reports, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Human Developments"- Newsletter, Fall 1971 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - The Connection - Human Development Newsletter, 1989-1994 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - The Connection - Human Development Newsletter, 1984-1988 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - The Connection - Human Development Newsletter, 1979-1983 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Pre-Adolescents- Why is each one Different?, 1964 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Pre-Adolescents- Striving for Independence, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Pre-Adolescents- The Importance of Peers, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - "People Who've Made It"-research summaries-Dr. Harold Feldman, 198? (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - "Men and the ERA"--Dr. Harold Feldman, Denise Lowell and Judy Zimbalist (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - Resources for Parents and Others Who Care About Children (HDFS #3, 4, 6-10, 12-19, 24 and 50), 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "Day Care Now" by Jane Knitzer (Box 26, Folder 16)